My name's Heather Browning, and I'm here on behalf of my daughter, Bronwyn,
who has multiple myeloma. I'm accompanied by Barbara and
Nicola from Myeloma New Zealand, who'll speak to the broader
issues and concerns for people across Aotearoa with
myeloma. I'll speak very specifically to the situation for
my whanau.
I just want to give you some context to our situation.
In 1999, I was diagnosed with Stage 2B cervical
cancer. It was a large tumor, it'd gone undetected despite
regular pap smears, et cetera.
My daughter, Bronwyn, my only child, was just 10 years old,
and I was solo parenting at the time.
And at that time, things looked pretty grim,
and through the following year of radiotherapy and
surgeries. Clearly, I've survived,
and also prevailed through two episodes of melanoma.
Nonetheless, those years were pretty tough for my daughter.
Fast-forward to 2017, when the first of my three brothers
succumbed to metastatic lung cancer.
In May 2018, the second of my brothers died, also from lung
cancer. And just over one year later, in June
2019, my remaining brother died from
invasive colorectal cancer. Again,
those were dark days for my daughter and me.
My three brothers, Bronwyn's beloved uncles, were all gone within two
years of one another.
So we moved on, and just when we thought we could really move on, and after
COVID,
in February 2022, Bronwyn
was diagnosed with multiple myeloma.
She was 33 years old.
Apparently very young to be receiving such a diagnosis, a fact that
was tediously noted to us by every health professional she
encountered.
So to say that we were shocked
or distraught or overwhelmed by this news is a massive
understatement.
The cancer legacy, it's terrible.
The cancer legacy in our whanau is very confronting
and something that Bronwyn has lived with throughout her life.
But there's a stark difference between the nature of cancers and the
available treatments of my brothers and me versus the
situation for Bronwyn.
We all had preventable or avoidable cancers
if we'd known at the time, at crucial stages in our lives, what to avoid
or have had access to
screening that's now available.
And once diagnosed, we all had a range of options for treatment,
including radiotherapy, chemotherapy, and surgeries.
That's how it is with tumor cancers,
but none of that is how it is with blood cancers, with
myeloma. Myeloma has no known cause,
so there's no mechanisms for prevention.
There is no screening program, and diagnoses are most
often arrived at incidentally when a person presents
with some other vague ailment or pain.
But the greater jeopardy with myeloma
is that the treatment options in Aotearoa are extremely limited
and are way out of kilter with other OECD countries.
Stem cell transplants are not curative.
They simply delay the inevitable,
and the maintenance options are limited.
Throughout 2022, Bronwyn went through the necessary processes of
chemotherapy prior to an autologous stem cell transplant
in November 2022.
This pushed her into remission, thankfully, and to date, she remains in
remission,
but on a maintenance program, a regime of
lenalidomide.
As a result of the initial chemotherapy, Bronwyn is
now unable to have children,
and that's been a very high price for her and her husband.
Nonetheless, they've designed a good life for themselves, and she's
choosing as much as she is able not to be defined by
myeloma. She's currently studying for her
master's in zoology, which is where her passion is and where she focuses
her energy.
Hence me talking to you. She's using
lenalidomide to hold myeloma at bay, but it's a
double-edged sword.
While it is a lifeline of sorts, it's a terrible drug with an array of awful
side effects that impact daily on her quality of life and wellbeing.
To add to those challenges, the long-term use of lenalidomide can
create new risks for other cancers, but Bron has no
choice. She's no other options here in Aotearoa.
Bron knows that she will not remain in remission
indefinitely. She knows it's just a matter of time.
It's an ever-present shadow for her.
She's hoping, well, I guess we're all hoping,
that her remission will last long enough that other options for treatment become
available. Things like immunotherapies,
CAR T-cell therapy, et cetera. All those options that are currently
available in many other countries.
We want those for her in Aotearoa.
I want my daughter to have more than hope.
Hope isn't enough. We've been there, done that. Hope doesn't work.
Hope alone is an injustice. It's an energy thief
if there's not something tangible and meaningful to hope for.
So we need certainty that in the very near future, Bronwyn
and all the others in a situation like hers will have
treatment options that give the opportunity for her to have a full,
long, and enjoyable life.
That's me. Thank you.
I'll pass over to Barbara
Thanks, Heather.
Kia ora and good morning. I'm Barbara Horn, chair of Myeloma New
Zealand, and joined today by Nicola Oakenvill.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak with you about only three, we're
only going to choose three, of the issues facing New Zealand's myeloma
community and what can be done about them.
Some background, more than 3,500 New Zealanders are living with
myeloma, with over 450 newly diagnosed each year.
While the average age at diagnosis is between 65 and 70,
New Zealand patients range in age from their 20s.
Māori and Pasifika experience higher diagnosis rates, they are
diagnosed younger, and they have lower survival rates.
Myeloma is a relentless cancer of the plasma cells found in
bone marrow, and it's a relapsing-remitting cancer.
So that means it can respond to treatment and go into remission, and then it
will come back. Imagine how this plays out.
You get diagnosed with something you've probably never heard of.
There's a line of treatment that might or might not work.
If it fails or causes debilitating side effects, or if it works for
a while and then you relapse, as you will, you can't keep using the same
treatment, so there is another line, and another line, then another.
But not in New Zealand.
That's the way it is in countries where access to medicines makes myeloma a
chronic but manageable disease. But not here.
And that's issue number one, access to modern medicines and
treatments.
In New Zealand, you are diagnosed, you begin the regime of weekly hospital
visits and learn this new complex language of myeloma, and you and your
people work out how to manage this new normal, and the frustration
begins of feeling there is very little anyone can do to help.
New Zealand treatment options for myeloma are very limited, and they include
thalidomide, a 70-year-old medicine with some history.
While it can be a viable medicine to use, it and the other medicines readily
available and funded here are generally old, less
effective, and less patient-friendly than modern medicines.
Newer treatments are easier to tolerate, they provide effective treatment for
longer, and allow patients to live a more normal life with
longer times between the inevitable relapses.
The issue of access to modern medicines also has an implication for
access to clinical trials. These are an essential tool for clinicians and
patients as a way to access newer medicines.
The reality is, New Zealand hematologists often cannot accept trials
because daratumumab is not available here.
This standard of care medicine, funded in more than 50 countries, is often a
comparator or a prerequisite treatment for trial participation.
Issue two is that funding just one more medicine will not be a silver bullet.
Myeloma is highly individual, so clinicians need a range of medicines
they can combine and sequence for each patient.
To do this, Australia funds five more myeloma treatments than New
Zealand, and the UK funds nine more.
The reality of these two issues is that New Zealanders with myeloma die earlier
than they need to. Those who can pay for unfunded treatments
often take drastic options to fund treatment privately in New Zealand or
overseas.
And issue three then is that even private health insurance may not
provide access.
Although a patient may have sufficient cover for non-PharmAC-funded
medicines, that cover is likely to apply
only to Medsafe-registered medicines.
The currently low likelihood of new treatments being funded by PharmAC
can discourage pharmaceutical companies from registering these modern
life-prolonging myeloma medicines in New Zealand.
This means a myeloma patient in New Zealand with private medical insurance
will likely have access to fewer medicines than a publicly treated
patient in Australia.
To be clear, we're not suggesting the solution for these issues is fanciful
or experimental treatment. We're simply asking for access to
medicines that are standard of care internationally, medicines that help
people with this unrelenting disease live longer and continue
contributing to their families and communities.
And yes, we do understand that there is a cost to these modern medicines,
but cost is only one side of the equation.
The other side is that with modern medicines, myeloma can be a very
livable cancer that doesn't clog up the health system.
Patients continue working, looking after children and grandchildren,
volunteering, coaching sports teams, living full, productive
lives, and contributing.
You can help make that happen.
Thank you.
Thank you, Barbara. Thank you, Heather.
We've got a minute or two for questions.
Do any members want to ask anything?
It doesn't appear so. Thank you very much, though, for coming in and
raising more awareness around myeloma
and blood cancers, and all of the challenges that you guys are
facing on a personal level, and our sincere
sympathies for that.
Thank you for raising this to the committee. Have a good day.
Thank you for the opportunity. Thank you. Stay warm.
Thank you.
Okay, we'll move back to private session, please.